This task is about immediate
consequence operator tp.
Our task is to compute the first three
iterations of tp starting with the empty set.
We start with the empty set as the
Herbrand interpretation as argument for tp.
We write tp of the empty set equals and then we
write to set that this iteration consists of.
For this first set we have to consider
only the facts of our prolog program.
In contrast to the example in the lecture for tp
in this case we do not have
any variables in our facts.
Our facts are just without variables.
We can just simply include
all the facts in this set.
We have ingredient(salad)
in our set and all the other
ingredients so: ingredient(salami),
ingredient(carrot), ingredient(steak).
So it's all all the predicates for ingredients
that are part of the tp of the empty set.
And beside the ingredients
there are also the veggies.
Those are just the two: salad
and carrot; and the predicate
carbs – there's just a single one –
so only fries is a carb in this case.
Finally there's the predicate compose
where we have fries and steak as fact.
So compose(fries, steak) as a fact
so this is part of tp as well.
As I said before, this is a set, so we need to
separate all the members of the set by comma,
okay?
This is the first iteration of tp.
There are no further elements within
tp because there are no more facts left
and there are no variables
within our effects, okay?
We continue with the second iteration
which is tp of tp of the empty set.
This one contains a tp of the empty set.
This is part of the set but
there are also more members and
so we can unify tp and the empty set
with those members that are left.
Now we consider the rules.
We consider all the rules but only those
where on the right hand side, beginning with
the implication arrow, there are predicates
which are in tp of the empty set already.
That's why we can consider all the veggie
ingredients parts and carbs, but we can not
apply this sidedish because we don't have a
sidedish within our tp of the empty set yet.
So in our previous iteration there is no sidedish
that's why we can only consider
compose and not sidedish.
For compose we have to consider
x and y and x and y are
a veggie of x and ingredient of y in this case.
So everything we find that is requiring a veggie
and an ingredient we can add it to compose, okay?
We can compose every veggie with every ingredient.
So we can say compose
of salad and carrot for instance.
Because carrot is an ingredient, right?
Furthermore we can combine it with every
other ingredient as well right away.
So this is one member of the set.
We can compose salad also with salami.
Salami is is like a pepperoni on a pepperoni pizza
- so it's some german version of a meat product.
(add space some space here)
We can compose salad with
carrot, with salami, with salad.
We can compose salad with steak and
we can compose salad with fries.
This is the first part, which
is a veggie and an ingredient.
But there's another veggie as
well and this one is carrot.
– We can use all the things we had here –
With carrot as well so you could simply
copy this part here and replace
all these salads with carrot.
Just as a side note: it's perfectly
fine to combine carrot with carrot
and it's also perfectly fine
to combine salad with salad.
That's just how these these predicates work.
Then there's no veggie left.
We have all the veggies combined
with all the ingredients.
This is the cross product
of veggie and ingredient.
Now we have the compose left for carbs.
Now we have to apply the compose
with carbs and every ingredient.
Again we can copy this stuff here and this
time we have, as I said, the carbs to choose.
And carbs is just fries.
We can combine it with every ingredient again.
But this is not completely true
because there's one ingredient
or one combination that's mentioned already here.
So fries is already combined with steak so
we do not enter this one here because it
would be a duplicate and as we
have a set there are no duplicates.
This is our set for the second iteration.
Why is there no side dish here?
Because we could compose a compose
with a veggie and a carb here and then
we would have a side dish as well, okay?
But in this case we would have required
the second component a veggie or a carb.
But if we have a look here
- in these um composes here
that we have in the previous
step - it's only fries and steak.
There is no predicate veggie for steak and there
is neither a predicate for carbs for steak.
None of them is available.
So we can't add the predicate sidedish
with any parameter in this step here.
And just to further highlight this.
I just want to show for some examples that we
created by choosing parts of the first iteration.
I said that we had first a look at the compose.
So it's this compose here.
This requires a veggie and an ingredient.
We could choose any veggie – for instance salad
– and any ingredient – for instance carrot.
When we combine them then this
is this part for instance, right?
We could combine those two from the previous
step in order to get this new entry here.
And we have combined salad also with salami,
with steak that's this one, with salad
well, and carrot – I mentioned already, and fries.
We combined it always with those parts here.
Every combination is possible here in this
case, because it's exactly the predicates
that we match here on the right hand side.
Now we continue with the next iteration of tp.
Right here let's go a bit down
to make more space for this.
This is the next iteration of tp and
this is tp of tp of tp of the empty set.
For this iteration again: it
consists of the previous step.
It's tp of tp of the empty set unified
with the new members of this set now.
Just as a side note as tp of tp of
the empty set is member of this set,
tp of the empty set is also a member because this
is also a member of the previous step, right?
So all the previous steps are members.
This is the second step now when we combine
or take the other rules into account.
We do not have to look at the compose anymore
because we've got already all composes within
either tp of tp of the empty
set or tp of the empty set.
Now we can continue by looking for predicates
that are applicable or rules that are applicable.
fullmeal is not applicable
because we have no sidedish yet.
But sidedish is applicable because we have
composes and we have veggies and carbs.
veggies and carbs are in tp of
the empty set and composes are
in both tp of the empty set
and tp of tp of the empty set.
Now we can create sidedishes
by composing a compose.
This is a carrot, salad, and fries
combined with a veggie (or a carb)
Let's consider this rule first.
We compose any of these –
salad, carrot, and fries.
So we have all combinations for
salad, carrot, and fries with veggie.
Let's start with salad.
Now we can choose any veggie.
Veggies are salad and carrot..
So we can add the sidedish
that is salad and salad.
We can have a sidedish hat
is salad combined with carrot,
because this is also a veggie.
And then we have this other rule here.
These were all the veggies
but we have this other rule
to combine a sidedish with
a carb and this is fries.
So we can
combine this also with fries.
salad and fries is also a sidedish.
I think I continue a bit further on the left
just in order to use a bit more
of the space available here.
Now we had the salad already, so we can
choose composes with carrot and with fries.
Let's continue with the carrots
A side dish of carrot and –
Again we can only choose veggies
and carbs for the second component.
So steak and salami are no options.
But we can choose carrot, salad and fries.
Because carrot, salad and fries
happen to be either veggies or carbs.
So either they apply for this rule or that rule.
It's carrot and salad is a
sidedish, also carrot and
carrot, and a sidedish is carrot and fries.
And once more we can apply the whole thing.
First we can use the sidedish
rule again for the fries part.
So we have composes with fries
and every other ingredient.
So we can say a sidedish of fries and
– again we have to consider the rules.
The rules just say a sidedish is
if it is a compose and veggie.
There are all combinations of compose
with fries as the first component.
But only carrot, salad, and
fries are either veggie or carbs.
Salami is neither of them.
Again we have the combination fries and salad,
sidedish fries and carrot, and finally sidedish
fries and fries.
That's the third iteration.
Now we come to the fourth
iteration of tp of tp and so on
So this is tp of tp of tp of tp of the
empty set.
(bracket here)
As before it consists of tp
of tp of tp of the empty set
combined with all the members
of this iteration on it.
So we have the first tp of the empty set, we have
tp of tp of the empty set, and we have tp of tp
of tp of the empty set – that's the previous step.
And now it is – well it's actually actually
fourth iteration now, but still
let's let's finish it here.
We have this fourth iteration because
we don't have applied all rules yet.
For the actual task it would be
enough to end with this iteration
but as there are still steps left we can
continue with the fourth iteration here.
The rule that's missing is fullmeal.
A fullmeal consists of sidedish(x,
y) with sidedish(y, z).
So a fullmeal has to be a sidedish where the
second component of a sidedish is also part of a
first component of a sidedish.
We can create all the combinations that
are possible for this fullmeal definition.
A full meal consists of a sidedish and a sidedish.
As sidedishes are only in this iteration
because here in these iterations there is no
side dish so we can just have
a look at these ones here.
And we have fullmeals for sidedishes that
contain the first part and a component being the
second second part and also
as first part of a sidedish.
So a valid combination would be:
sidedish(salad, salad) and sidedish(salad,
salad) which would result in the
fullmeal(salad, salad, salad), right?
Because if we apply this here to this rule – x and
y is salad and salad – and y and z is salad
and salad then x, y, z is salad, salad, salad.
We can continue by using this sidedish here
as the first component – so salad and salad –
and combine it with all the other parts which are
also valid predicates here for the second part.
So salad and salad is the first
first part for x and y and then we
can combine it with salad and carrot
because the first component is salad
and the second component is carrot
– so it's a valid option here.
We can continue the whole thing, i think.
fullmeal is also salad, and salad, and fries
which is the last available option here.
We can check if there is another option
where salad is the first component.
But if you have a look here we see there
is no other option – so these are the
only valid options for salad and
salad as the first two components.
We can continue the same with
salad and something else.
We can say: a full meal is something which is
of salad and carrot which is our second option.
We can just continue by choosing the next option
which is a good way of continuing the whole thing.
Now we have a salad and carrot set
for x and y so y has to be carrot
and now we can choose all these sidedishes
with carrot which are these three.
We can combine all the options so we have fullmeal
for salad, carrot, and salad as well as for
salad, carrot, and carrot and
also for salad, carrot, and fries.
We can continue with the fullmeal further.
There's no other option for carrot
here so carrot is already done.
We can now continue with salad and fries.
When salad and fries is set – salad
is set for x and fries is set for y
so z has to be something where
the first component is fries.
So any of these and those are again salad,
carrot, and fries.
It's salad, fries, and salad;
salad, fries, and carrot; and salad,
fries, and fries.
These are the first options.
We can continue the whole thing for
the next part, that is for all the
things that are sidedishes starting with
carrot and then also the ones with fries.
If we do this then we can continue here.
Like combining carrot with
salad which is the first option.
Then we can choose salad again.
We can choose for carrot, salad,
carrot; and we can choose for carrot,
salad, and fries.
This is the third option.
We can continue with carrot and carrot.
This is the second option we have
here for carrot as first part.
When we choose carrot and carrot.
We can choose carrot and
salad as the first component.
carrot as the second option.
We can choose carrot and
fries as the third option.
And we can continue with carrot and fries
as the first sidedish of the full meal.
If we do this then we have
carrot, fries and salad as option.
Because fries and salad is a valid option
for the second part as well and fries and
carrot is also an option.
If we choose carrot and fries as the
first option – as first sidedish – we can
have fries and fries as the second sidedish.
We can continue like this
very straight forward also for fries
which is the last available component.
And for fries we can apply the same stuff
so we can look in the first part here.
Of salad and salad, salad and carrots, salad and
fries – so these are these three options that are
valid combinations for the
first sidedish fries and salad.
Then for the sidedish fries and carrot again
we have all the options of those three.
The combination fries, fries
and fries which is the last one.
So we have all the fries options available.
When we are done with this, then we have the
complete set of the the fourth iteration.
And if we would continue with the next
iteration we would finally find out that
the next iteration does not add anything more.
Because there's no rule which is not applied yet.
We have applied all the rules with all
the combinations that are available.
So this is the final set of the smallest Herbrand
model that we can get by applying tp once
more or applying tp as often as required.
In this case it's four
iterations when we are done.
As i said before already, this is the first
iteration, the second iteration, third iteration.
So we would have done the task
already by finishing here.
This iteration is an additional
for completing the fourth iteration and
also completing what's the complete set.
As I said, if you would apply tp
once more you would not gain anything
else because all the rules are applied
and this is the smallest Herbrand model.